Register of the Paul Haensel (Pavel Petrovich Genzel') Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Paul Haensel (Pavel Petrovich Genzel') papers
1907-1950
2000C43
Hoover Institution Archives
14 microfilm reels (2.1 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, correspondence, curricular materials, and printed matter, relating to economic conditions and especially to tax policy, primarily in the United States.
Haensel, Paul, b. 1878
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
Professor Paul Haensel was a prominent economist who authored several books on taxation and finance and taught at Northwestern University from 1930 to 1943. Haensel was born in Moscow on 8 February 1878 (N.S.). Graduating from the Moscow Practical Commercial Academy in 1896, he entered Moscow University, completing his course of studies in 1902 with a degree in law. Remaining at the University as a professor from 1903 to 1928, he published many works on taxation, including his master's thesis, Nalog s nasledstva (1906), as well as works on public finance, such as Istoriia finansov (1913) and Finansovaia reforma v Rossii (1916-1917). In addition to his teaching and research activities, he served as a member of the board of directors of the State Bank, 1915-1917, advisor to the Commissariat of Finance, and director of the financial section of the Institute of Economic Research in Moscow, 1921-1928.
Invited to lecture abroad in 1928, he opted to remain there, finding a position as professor of economics in 1930. He taught and wrote on Soviet as well as American and European economic issues, and testified before Congressional committees on tax reform in 1943. Following his retirement from Northwestern in that year, he continued to teach at Mary Washington College of the University of Virginia until 1948. Haensel died in Illinois on 28 February 1949.
Chronology
1878 February 8 Born, Moscow, Russia
1902 LLD, Moscow University
1903-1928 Professor of finance, Moscow University
1908-1916 Dean, Economics Department, Moscow Commercial Institute
1928 Visiting lecturer, London School of Economics
1929-1930 Professor, Universität Graz, Austria
1930-1943 Professor, Northwestern University, Evanston, Illinois
1943-1948 Professor, Mary Washington College, Fredericksburg, Virginia
1949 February 28 Died
Scope and Content Note
This collection reflects the academic career and public service in the United States of the notable Russian economist Paul Haensel. As professor of economics at Northwestern University and Mary Washington College, he lectured and wrote widely on topics of taxation, public finance and international economics. A significant amount of material in the collection details his involvement in debates over taxation policy in the U.S. before and during World War II.
Also of interest are his short stories and novel of life in the Russia during and after the Revolution (Speeches and writings/"Top'," "Zhizn' krutit," "Amerikanskaia duel'"). Many of his writings are brief newspaper notes, articles, or letters to the editor on various subjects; these, along with his notes for speeches, are grouped together by physical form. Only more significant speeches and writings have been given separate entries.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming of these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials are held at the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco, as its property. A transfer table of corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Economics.; Economists.; Russia.; Russians--United States.; Taxation--United States.; United States--Economic conditions.; United States--Politics and government.
- Biographical File, 1928-1950 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Addresses, clippings, identity papers, scrapbook and other material arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1933-1947 (Box 2)
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent
- Speeches and Writings, 1923-1949 (Box 2-7)
  Arranged chronologically by title
- Course Materials, 1907-1948 (Box 7-12)
  Lectures, notes, syllabi and related materials, arranged alphabetically by name of university and therein by course title
- Printed Matter, 1934-1948 (Box 13-14)
  Mainly clippings from Russian and American newspapers, on a variety of subjects (economics, taxation, Russian history, Soviet politics, emigration, etc.)
- Photographs, 1909-1943 (Box 14)
  Fourteen photographs of Haensel, family members and unidentified figures
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1928-1950 (Box 1)
  - Addresses, 1943-1947 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Bibliography (Folder 1: 2)
  - Clippings about or mentioning Haensel
    - General, 1935-1948 (Folder 1: 3)
      General note
      See also SPEECHES AND WRITINGS/General/Newspaper interviews
    - Death notices and obituaries, 1949 (Folder 1: 4)
    - Incident with Professor Schilpp, 1937 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Curriculum vitae (Folder 1: 6)
  - Family file
    - Clippings, 1940-1942 (Folder 1: 7)
    - Correspondence, 1949 and undated (Folder 1: 8)
      Telegram and letter of Nina Haensel (widow) to P. F. Konstantinov, and letter of Konstantin Haensel to Mr. Kelso, n.d.
    - Writing. Antipin, P. P., "Kolossal'nyi uspekh uchenika Prof. V. N. Ipat'eva,"., 1950 November 6 (Folder 1: 9)
      Typescript
  - Identity card, 1928 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Inventory of archive (Folder 1: 11)
  - Lecture notices (Folder 1: 12)
  - Press releases (Folder 1: 13)
  - Scrapbook. (Folder 1: 14)
    Includes clippings of articles by, about or mentioning Haensel
  - Miscellany (Folder 1: 15)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1933-1947 (Box 2)
  - General, 1937-1947 (Folder 2: 1)
  - Unidentified, n.d. (Folder 2: 2)
  - Brooks, C. Wayland, Sen., 1940-1947 and undated (Folder 2: 3)
  - Carlson, Frank, Rep., 1943 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Case, Francis H., 1941 (Folder 2: 5)
  - Church, Ralph E., Rep., 1943-1947 (Folder 2: 6)
  - Corson, John J., 1940-1941 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Dewey, Charles S., Rep., 1941-1944 (Folder 2: 8)
  - Doughton, Robert L., Rep., 1943 (Folder 2: 9)
  - Forand, Aime J., Rep., 1943 (Folder 2: 10)
  - Garrigan, Robert E., 1937 (Folder 2: 11)
  - George, Walter F., Sen., 1943 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Howard, Mayne S., 1934 (Folder 2: 13)
  - MacGregor, Professor, n.d. (Folder 2: 14)
  - McCormick, Robert, 1942 (Folder 2: 15)
  - National Association of Manufacturers. Statistical Department, 1936 (Folder 2: 16)
  - National Council of Real Estate Taxpayers, 1942 (Folder 2: 17)
  - New York Times, 1942-1947 (Folder 2: 18)
  - Northwestern University, 1933-1941 (Folder 2: 19)
  - Paddock, George A., Rep., 1941-1942 (Folder 2: 20)
  - Peyster, Mr., 1937 (Folder 2: 21)
  - Robertson, A. Willis, Rep., 1941-1945 (Folder 2: 22)
  - Rothschild, Meyer D., 1942 (Folder 2: 23)
  - Seidman, M. L., 1942 (Folder 2: 24)
  - Stevenson, Mr., 1935 (Folder 2: 25)
  - Traylor, Melvin A., 1933 (Folder 2: 26)
  - Treadway, Allen T., Rep., 1942 (Folder 2: 27)
  - United States. Civil Service Commission, 1942 (Folder 2: 28)
  - United States. Congress. House of Representatives. Committee on Ways and Means, 1941-1947 (Folder 2: 29)
    For correspondence with individual Congressmen, see also personal names
  - United States. Congress. Senate, 1941-1947 (Folder 2: 30)
  - United States. Department of the Treasury, 1941-1942 (Folder 2: 31)
  - United States. Federal Security Agency. Social Security Board. Bureau of Old-Age and Survivors Insurance.
    See Corson, John J.
  - United States. Office of Price Administration, 1942 (Folder 2: 32)
  - United States. Office of Strategic Services, 1944-1945 (Folder 2: 33)
    Includes correspondence with Office of Volunteer Readings
  - United States. Office of the Postmaster General, 1942 (Folder 2: 34)
  - Watkins, E. F., 1935 (Folder 2: 35)
  - Weiss, Samuel A., Rep., 1942 (Folder 2: 36)
  - Williams, Frankwood E., 1936 (Folder 2: 37)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1923-1949
  See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE/Press releases for Haensel's pronouncements on tax questions
  - General
    - Book reviews, 1938-1945 and undated (Folder 2: 38)
      Holograph, typescript and printed copies
    - Letters to the editor, 1930-1948 (Folder 2: 39)
    - Newspaper columns (Box 3)
      - General, 1937-1948 (Folder 3: 1)
        Printed copies
      - "Obo vsem ponemnogu,"., 1945-1946 (Folder 3: 2)
    - Newspaper interviews, 1935-1943 (Folder 3: 3)
      See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE/Clippings, and Press releases
      Printed copies.
    - Notes and typed fragments, primarily on taxation issues (Folder 3: 4)
    - Speeches, 1929-1942 and undated (Folder 3: 5)
      Consists mainly of notes for speeches and talks on subjects of taxation and current events
  - "Bibliography on Russia,", n.d. (Folder 3: 6)
    Holograph and typescript. Includes background materials
  - "The Comparative Effect of a Sales Tax, of an Income Tax, of a Spendings Tax, and of the 5% Victory Tax on the Lower Income Brackets," (Folder 3: 7)
    Holograph
  - "The Cost of Living in Soviet Russia,", n.d. (Folder 3: 8)
  - "The Economic Situation in Soviet Russia,", n.d. (Folder 3: 9)
    Holograph and typescript
  - "The Inflation Havoc,", n.d. (Folder 3: 10)
  - "The International Institute of Public Finance,", n.d. (Folder 3: 11)
  - "The Kremlin of Moscow,", n.d. (Folder 3: 12)
  - "A Man Who Does Not Know His Name,", n.d. (Folder 3: 13)
  - "La politica finanziaria americana per la ripresa economica,", n.d. (Folder 3: 14)
  - "The Principles of a Tax on Property,", n.d. (Folder 3: 15)
  - "Professor Haensel's Answers to Questions on the Post-War Tax System,", n.d. (Folder 3: 16)
  - "Relations between the USA and USSR," (Folder 3: 17)
  - "Should College Students Bear the Cost of Their Instruction?", n.d. (Folder 3: 18)
  - "Some Remarks on the Russian Recognition Agreement,", n.d. (Folder 3: 19)
  - "Sovetskaia mest' mirovym uchenym,", n.d. (Folder 3: 20)
  - "Der Staatshaushalt und das Finanzsystem Großbritanniens," Handbuch der Finazwissenschaft (Folder 3: 21)
    Printed copy
  - Statement before the U.S. Senate Finance Committee, n.d. (Folder 3: 22)
  - "Tax Incentives,", n.d. (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - "Taxation of the Future,", n.d. (Folder 4: 2)
  - "Les travaux publics pour le relèvement économique et la lutte contre le chômage aux Etats-Unis sous l'administration du Président Roosevelt," (Folder 4: 3)
  - Untitled review of the Russian situation during and after World War II (Folder 4: 4)
  - Untitled work on social security (missing first page), n.d. (Folder 4: 5)
  - "V. N. Ipatieff in Russia,", n.d. (Folder 4: 6)
  - "Vosstanovlenie Dnepro-Bugskogo kanala,", n.d. (Folder 4: 7)
  - "Why Sales Tax?", n.d. (Folder 4: 8)
  - "Top',"., 1923 July (Folder 4: 9-10)
    Typescript. Includes two drafts and letter to Liberty, 1933 March 25, regarding submission for contest
  - "Zhizn' krutit,"., 1924 July 29
    - Russian original. (Folder 4: 11-13)
      Includes three variants
    - German translation: "Im Wirbel des Lebens." (Folder 4: 14-16)
      Three drafts
    - English translation: "Life's Whirlpool." (Folder 4: 17-18)
      Two drafts
  - "Dve liubvi,"., 1925 July
    - Russian original (Folder 4: 19)
    - German translation: "Zweierlei Liebe." (Folder 4: 20-21)
  - "Some Pictures of the Present Day Russia,"., [1930] (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Review of István Varga, Die Wirtschaftspolitik Sowjetrusslands, in Közgazdasági Szemle, 1930 November (Folder 5: 2)
  - Untitled work on religion in the USSR, 1930 February (Folder 5: 3)
  - "Die Mittelschulbildung im Österreich,"., 1930 June (Folder 5: 4)
  - "The Causes of the Present Difficulties," ?, 1932 (Folder 5: 5)
  - "Prohibition - And What Next?"., 1932 May (Folder 5: 6)
    Typescript. Includes drafts and fragments
  - "Local Finance," Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences, 1933 (Folder 5: 7)
  - "Some Problems of the International Economic Conference,"., 1933 May 27 (Folder 5: 8)
  - "A Scientific Investigation,"., 1934 (Folder 5: 9)
  - "The Future American Foreign Investment Policy," paper read before the Midwest Economic Conference in Chicago, 1934 March 23 (Folder 5: 10)
  - "American Federal, State and Local Tax Problems in the Light of the Recovery Program," The Tax Magazine, 1934 October-December (Folder 5: 11)
    Printed copy. Includes summaries, correspondence and background material
  - "Pending Tax Legislation in California," address given at the Los Angeles University Club for the Southern California Tax Conference, 1935 February 5 (Folder 5: 12)
    Typescript. Includes background material and notes
  - Real Estate Taxation of the Future, 1935 February 6 (Folder 5: 13)
  - "Haensel Views Pension Plan," Evanston Daily News Index, 1935 April 23-24 (Folder 5: 14)
  - "How America Can Collect,"., 1935 May (Folder 5: 15)
  - "The Communist International," Chicago Tribune, 1935 August 29 (Folder 5: 16)
  - "Soak the Rich,"., 1936 January 12 (Folder 5: 17)
    Notes
  - "Soviet Russia's Unified Budget for 1936," The Tax Magazine, 1936 April (Folder 5: 18)
  - "K vyboram 3-go noiabria," Russkoe obozrenie, 1936 October 24 (Folder 5: 19)
  - Letter to the editor, Evanston Daily News-Index, 1936 September 28 (Folder 5: 20)
  - "The Pushkin Celebration,"., [1937] (Folder 5: 21)
  - "Die Ausshaltung des Profitmotivs,"., 1937 April 9 (Folder 5: 22)
  - "Dangerous Errors About Soviet Russia," Contemporary Russia, 1937 May (Folder 5: 23)
    Printed copy. Includes holograph and typed drafts entitled "The Webbs on Soviet Russia"
  - "Action Against a Slump," letter to the editor, The Times, 1937 June 10 (Folder 5: 24)
    Printed copy. Includes holograph drafts, background material and correspondence
  - "Eshche o novom kalendare," Russkoe obozrenie, 1937 August 14 – September 4 (Folder 5: 25)
  - "My Visit to Europe," speech, 1937 October 6 (Folder 5: 26)
  - Letter to the editor, Peoples' Lobby Bulletin, 1937 October 30 (Folder 5: 27)
    Holograph and typescript. Includes background material
  - "Why Dictators?" lecture at the University Circle, 1937 November 12 (Folder 5: 28)
  - "Anketa o russkikh v Soedinennykh Shtatakh," Rassvet, 1937 December 1 (Folder 5: 29)
  - "Public Debt of the United States Particularly with Reference to Its Retirement,"., [1938] (Folder 5: 30)
  - "The Public Finance of the Union of Soviet Socialistic Republics," The Tax Magazine, 1938 (Folder 5: 31)
    Review and summary of Haensel's article by P. J. A. A. in Bulletin for Intern. Fiscal Documentation, v. II, #4, n.d. Printed copy
  - "U razbitogo koryta," Russkoe obozrenie, 1938 January 8 (Folder 5: 32)
  - "Novaia depressiia," Russkoe obozrenie, 1938 February 19 (Folder 5: 33)
  - "Staraia depressiia," Russkoe obozrenie, 1938 February 26 (Folder 5: 34)
  - "The Russian Orthodox Church in America," Dictionary of American History, 1938, between April and June (Folder 5: 35)
    Typescript. Includes notes, draft and correspondence
  - "Soviet Foreign Trade," speech before Export Managers Club of Chicago, 1938 May 23 (Folder 5: 36)
    Notes and typed summary (press release)
  - "Finansovoe polozhenie S. Sh. A.," talk before the Russkoe Natsional'noe Obshchestvo, 1938 May 27 (Folder 5: 37)
  - "Re: Tax Situation," letter to the editor, 1938 July 9 (Folder 5: 38)
    Holograph, typescript and printed copy
  - "A Janitor's Enemy,"., 1939 (Folder 5: 39)
  - "Moi nabliudeniia v Evrope," Russkoe obozrenie, 1939 August 12 – October 7 (Folder 5: 40)
  - "Les réformes sociales aux Etats-Unis,"., 1940 February 16 (Folder 5: 41)
  - "Role of Russia in the Present European Conflict," talk at Holgate House, 1940 March 6 (Folder 5: 42)
  - "Foreign Trade of Soviet Russia, D & E Talk,"., 1940 May 26 (Folder 5: 43)
    Notes for a speech
  - "If Hitler Wins...,"., 1940 [July] (Folder 5: 44)
    Holograph. Includes letter to Prof. Crane, 1940 July 8
  - "Kogo vybirat' v prezidenty?" Rassvet, Rossiia, Russkoe obozrenie, 1940 [c. October] – November 1 (Box-folder 6: 1)
    Printed copy. Incomplete set of articles serialized in above newspapers
  - "Otvet na 'zadachu'," Russkoe obozrenie, 1940 November 9 (Folder 6: 2)
    Printed copy. Includes background material
  - "Ocherednye voprosy," Rossiia, 1940 December 11 – 1941 April 12 (Folder 6: 3)
  - The Place of Illinois in a Rational Scheme of Tax Reform, 1941 (Folder 6: 4)
  - "War Taxation," Taxes, 1941 February (Folder 6: 5)
    Printed copy. Includes excerpt entitled "Financial Problems in Case of War," Bankers Magazine, 1941 April. Printed copy
  - "Vazhneishaia zadacha sovetskogo pravosudiia," Rossiia, 1941 June 29 (Folder 6: 6)
  - "Usloviia mira,"., 1941 July (Folder 6: 7)
  - "Russian Economic Losses Through the German Invasion," Journal of Business, 1941 October (Folder 6: 8)
  - "Recent Changes in the Soviet Tax System," Taxes, 1941 November (Folder 6: 9)
  - "Politika razrusheniia," Rossiia, 1941 November 4 – November 22 (Folder 6: 10)
  - "Plan for Compulsory War Savings,"., 1941 December 29 (Folder 6: 11)
    Typescript. Includes correspondence with United States. Executive Office of the President. Bureau of the Budget, 1941-1942, clipping of newspaper interview, Daily Northwestern, 1942 February 17, and other clippings
  - El Trabajador Bajo el Comunismo (U. S. S. R.), 1942 (Folder 6: 12)
  - "A Survey of Soviet Labor Legislation," Illinois Law Review, 1942 January (Folder 6: 13)
  - "Amerikanskie finansy," Rossiia, 1942 February 13 – March 21 (Folder 6: 14)
  - "Forthcoming Revenue Act, 1942," speech at the Tax Club of Chicago, 1942 March 18 (Folder 6: 15)
  - "A Temporary Turnover Tax," Taxes, 1942 May (Folder 6: 16)
  - "A Plan for a U.S. 'Bonus War Loan'," Financial World, 1942 June 24 (Folder 6: 17)
    Printed copy. Includes correspondence
  - "The First State Sickness Insurance Law,"., [1942] (Folder 6: 18)
    Correspondence, 1942-1943
  - "Small Currency Shortage,"., 1942 October 2 (Folder 6: 19)
  - "War, Taxes, Business," speech at the American Bottlers of Carbonated Beverages Convention, 1942 November 10 (Folder 6: 20)
  - "The 1943 Tax Increases in USSR,". (Folder 6: 21)
  - "A Critique of the Ruml Plan and of Congressman Robertson's Plan, Contrasted with a 'Liberalized Advance Tax Payment System',"., [1943] (Folder 6: 22)
  - "What About the New Victory Tax?" Chicago Herald-American, 1943 January 10 (Folder 6: 23)
  - "Mr. Paul on the Sales Tax," Taxes, 1943 January (Folder 6: 24)
    Printed copy and fragment of typescript
  - "The Russian Church and American Friendship," address at a dinner-meeting of members of the Catholic Club and others in the hall of the Holy Trinity Cathedral, Chicago, 1943 February (Folder 6: 25)
  - "Inflation in Personal Experience," talk, Chicago, 1943 February 23 (Folder 6: 26)
    Holograph. Includes correspondence
  - "Democratizing the Debt," Trusts and Estates: The Journal of Capital Management, 1943 March (Folder 6: 27)
  - Unidentified fragment of a work on taxation problems, 1943 March 14 (Folder 6: 28)
  - "Economic Aspects of Post-War Reconstruction," Proceedings of the Fifth Annual Public Affairs Conference at the Principia College of Liberal Arts, Elsah, Illinois, 1943 April 9-10 (Folder 6: 29)
  - "For a United Economic Europe, Divested of Trade Barriers, After the War," Export Trade and Shipper, 1943 May 31. Abstract, Library of Congress Legislative Reference Service, 1943 June (Folder 6: 30)
  - "Additional Evidence Concerning the 10 Per Cent Retail Sales Tax," Congressional Record, 1943 June 18 (Folder 6: 31)
  - "A Critique of the New Treasury's Tax Proposal,"., 1943 October (Folder 6: 32)
  - Statement before the Committee on Ways and Means, U.S. House of Representatives, 1943 October 13 (Folder 6: 33)
  - "Finansovaia reforma," Russkoe obozrenie, 1943 October 30 – December 4 (Folder 6: 34)
  - "Retirement at 65," School and Society, 1943 November 13 (Folder 6: 35)
    Typescript and printed copy
  - "Obshchestvennaia meditsina," Russkaia zhizn', 1943 December 9 (Folder 6: 36)
  - "Some Corrections to Mr. Tolpin's Article on Education in Russia,"., [1944] (Folder 6: 37)
  - "Two Views on Controversy Now Raging Over Issue of Sales Tax," interview with Haensel, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 1944 February 6 (Folder 6: 38)
  - "Tax Simplification," letter to the editor, Washington Post, 1944 February 21 (Folder 6: 39)
    Holograph and printed copy
  - "'Confidence First': A Post-War Employment Plan,"., 1945 (Folder 6: 40)
    Holograph and typescript. Includes correspondence with Reader's Digest regarding publication, 1944
  - "Finansy i Niu-Dil'," Russkaia zhizn', 1944 October 24-28 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - "Soviet Finances," The Russian Orthodox Journal, 1945 March (Folder 7: 2)
  - "Some Post-War Economic Problems," talk before the Commerce Group, 1945 March 1 (Folder 7: 3)
  - "Subway Fare v. Sales Tax,"., 1945 March 31 (Folder 7: 4)
    Typescript. Includes background materials
  - "Piataia svoboda," Russkaia zhizn', 1945 April 27 (Folder 7: 5)
    Printed copy. Includes related material and several letters to the editor by Haensel on the same subject: "A Fifth Freedom Suggested," New York Times, 1946 May 22; "Freedom of Migration in Russia," New York Times, 1947 February 28; "Right to Emigrate," The Washington Post, 1947 May 6; "Ban on Exit from Russia," New York Times, 1947 July 13
  - "Why People Emigrate?" talk, Monroe High School, 1945 May 23 (Folder 7: 6)
  - "Amerikano-Sovietskiia otnosheniia," Russkaia zhizn', 1945 May 31 (Folder 7: 7)
  - "Osnovy Amerikano-Russkoi druzhby," Russkaia zhizn', 1945 June 2-5 (Folder 7: 8)
  - "Czarist Russia," letter to the editor, The New York Times, 1945 September 23 (Folder 7: 9)
    Printed copy. Includes background material and correspondence with The New York Times, 1945
  - "Financing Britain," letter to the editor, The Washington Post, 1945 September 23 (Folder 7: 10)
    Printed copy and holograph entitled, "The British Loan"
  - "Government Pay Raises," Letter to the editor, The Washington Post, 1945 November 11 (Folder 7: 11)
    Includes different version of letter, entitled "Concerning Civil Service," Richmond Times-Dispatch, 1945 November 15. Printed copies. Also includes holograph and typescript drafts, entitled "Civil Service Pay Rise"
  - "Again on Russia and Finland," letter to the editor, 1946 January 14 (Folder 7: 12)
    Holograph. Includes background material
  - "The Sales Tax," letter to the editor, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 1946 January 17 (Folder 7: 13)
  - "Vodka," letter to the editor, New York Times Magazine, c. 1946 March 3 (Folder 7: 14)
  - "Proving the Case?" letter to the editor, Richmond Times-Dispatch, 1946 April 15 (Folder 7: 15)
  - "Lord Keins," Russkaia zhizn', 1946 April 27 (Folder 7: 16)
    Typescript and printed copy. Includes letters to the editor on the same subject: "Sidelight on Keynes," Washington Post, 1946 April 25; "Lord Keynes Praised," The New York Times, 1946 April 30
  - "Piatilietnii plan 1946-1950 gg.," Russkaia zhizn', 1946 May 11-15 (Folder 7: 17)
  - "Eshche o novom piatilietnem planie 1946-1950 gg.," Russkaia zhizn', 1945 May 16-21 (Folder 7: 18)